<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-18T23:14:43+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">sal-log</title><subtitle>Documenting my journey on data science, (health-)tech and beyond</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Novel NLP-Based Approach for Stock Market Visualization and Insight generation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/nlp/finance/2024/02/15/StockViz.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Novel NLP-Based Approach for Stock Market Visualization and Insight generation" /><published>2024-02-15T13:55:47+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-15T13:55:47+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nlp/finance/2024/02/15/StockViz</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/nlp/finance/2024/02/15/StockViz.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="background">Background</h1>

<p>In the fast-evolving landscape of data science, financial data emerges as a prime candidate for analytical exploration, offering a unique blend of accessibility, voluminous datasets, and significant impact. Unlike many other data types, financial data skirts around privacy concerns, enabling researchers and analysts to delve deep into trends, patterns, and insights that drive market dynamics. The sheer volume of financial data, coupled with its direct influence on economic decisions, makes it an ideal playground for data scientists looking to make a tangible impact.</p>

<p>Historically, the visualization of stock market data was a cumbersome affair, with lengthy tables sprawled across financial journals, challenging even the most dedicated readers to decipher trends and make informed decisions. This method of representation, while comprehensive, was far from efficient or user-friendly, often leading to information overload without offering clear, actionable insights. The evolution of data visualization tools and techniques has significantly changed this narrative, making data more accessible and interpretable.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/paper.png" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<h1 id="this-blog-post">This blog post</h1>
<p>This blog post introduces a new approach to stock market visualization using natural language processing and manifold learning techniques. 
The technique allows to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>group companies in fine-grained data-driven cluster going beyond the 11 traditional industrial sectors defined to the Global Industry Classification Standard</li>
  <li>find the most similar company given a selected company</li>
  <li>search NYSE semantically based on specific keywords</li>
  <li>identify trends, patterns, and relationships between different stocks or sectors that might not be obvious through traditional data analysis methods</li>
  <li>uncover investment opportunities in companies that are pioneering unique approaches or operating at the intersection of multiple industries.</li>
</ul>

<figure style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/assets/finviz-heat-map.png" alt="Alt text" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto; max-width: 100%; height: auto;" />
  <figcaption>Your caption here</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Traditional tools, such as the heatmaps found on platforms like <a href="https://finviz.com/map.ashx">FinViz</a>, provide a simplistic overview of market conditions, where the positioning of stocks is arbitrary and lacks deeper meaning. The solution proposed in this post goes beyond this, leveraging a custom-made text dataset to create a more representative and insightful visualization. By encoding meaningful relationships and dynamics between stocks, our method offers a nuanced understanding of the market, enabling users to make more informed decisions based on a sophisticated analysis of underlying patterns and trends.</p>

<h1 id="data-collection">Data collection</h1>
<p>As in any data science activity, developing a new visualization requires a comprehensive data collection process. To ensure we have a robust dataset at our disposal, we start by retrieving all active tickers on the New York Stock Exchange (NYSE). This is achieved through an FTP fetch of the files provided by <a href="ftp.nasdaqtrader.com">nasdaqtrader.com</a>. This initial step is crucial, as it lays the groundwork for our subsequent analysis, ensuring that we have a sufficiently large and complete snapshot of the market to work with.</p>

<p>Following the collection of ticker symbols, our next step involves deepening our understanding of each company behind these tickers. To accomplish this, we use to <a href="https://pypi.org/project/yfinance/">yfinance</a>, a powerful tool that allows us to retrieve short business summaries/descriptions for each company. This step  provides us with the natural language data necessary to understand the business context behind the numbers. By leveraging yfinance, we can extract rich, descriptive information about a company’s operations, market position, and strategic focus, which are input to the later advanced visualization techniques.</p>

<h1 id="data-analysis">Data analysis</h1>
<p>The core of the proposed methodology lies in the innovative use of NLP techniques to process the company descriptions (longBusinessSummaries by yfinance). By applying sparse vector representation through TF-IDF (Term Frequency-Inverse Document Frequency), dense word vector embedding, and contextual sentence embeddings, we transform textual information into a format that can be easily analyzed. These embedding techniques allow us to capture the nuances of each company’s business model and strategic positioning in a multidimensional space. This rich, embedded dataset serves as the foundation for our manifold learning-based visualization, enabling us to create a market representation where the proximity between stocks conveys meaningful similarities and differences in company business models and operations. Through this sophisticated approach, we aim to offer users a more intuitive and insightful view of the stock market, highlighting connections that were previously missed in traditional visualizations.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T-distributed_stochastic_neighbor_embedding">t-SNE</a>, or t-distributed Stochastic Neighbor Embedding, is a sophisticated manifold learning technique designed to make sense of complex data by simplifying it into a format that’s easier to understand and visualize, particularly well-suited for high-dimensional data. Imagine you have a room full of people who speak different languages, come from various professions, and have diverse hobbies. If you tried to map out their similarities and differences on a flat piece of paper, you’d quickly run out of room and clarity. t-SNE helps by finding a way to represent these complex relationships in a two or three-dimensional space, making it possible to see patterns and groupings at a glance. It does so by focusing on preserving the relationships between points (in this case, companies) rather than their absolute positions in the high-dimensional space. This means companies that are ‘‘similar’’ in the high-dimensional space (based on our business-oriented embeddings) will end up close to each other on a 2D or 3D map, even if they would be considered as vastly different in other ways not captured by the analysis. More <a href="https://lvdmaaten.github.io/tsne/">background information from the original author of the method</a></p>

<h1 id="results">Results</h1>
<p>We started from an universe of 7896 tickers. After removing tickers for which information was incomplete on yfinance (e.g. ETF related tickers lacking a business description), 5344 tickers were considered.
The corresponding ticker count per sector:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">sector</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">count</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Financial Services</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">1469</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Healthcare</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">1032</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Technology</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">597</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Industrials</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">534</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Consumer Cyclical</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">475</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Real Estate</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">255</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Energy</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">234</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Basic Materials</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">226</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Communication Services</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">225</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Consumer Defensive</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">202</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Utilities</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">95</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Examples of company descriptions derived using yfinance:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘Tesla, Inc. designs, develops, manufactures, leases, and sells electric vehicles, and energy generation and storage systems in the United States, China, and internationally. The company operates in two segments, Automotive, and Energy Generation and Storage. The Automotive segment offers electric vehicles, as well as sells automotive regulatory credits. It provides sedans and sport utility vehicles through direct and used vehicle sales, a network of Tesla Superchargers, and in-app upgrades; and purchase financing and leasing services. This segment is also involved in the provision of non-warranty after-sales vehicle services, sale of used vehicles, retail merchandise, and vehicle insurance, as well as sale of products to third party customers; services for electric vehicles through its company-owned service locations, and Tesla mobile service technicians; and vehicle limited warranties and extended service plans. The Energy Generation and Storage segment engages in the design, manufacture, installation, sale, and leasing of solar energy generation and energy storage products, and related services to residential, commercial, and industrial customers and utilities through its website, stores, and galleries, as well as through a network of channel partners. This segment also offers service and repairs to its energy product customers, including under warranty; and various financing options to its solar customers. The company was formerly known as Tesla Motors, Inc. and changed its name to Tesla, Inc. in February 2017. Tesla, Inc. was incorporated in 2003 and is headquartered in Austin, Texas.’</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘Apple Inc. designs, manufactures, and markets smartphones, personal computers, tablets, wearables, and accessories worldwide. It also sells various related services. In addition, the company offers iPhone, a line of smartphones; Mac, a line of personal computers; iPad, a line of multi-purpose tablets; and wearables, home, and accessories comprising AirPods, Apple TV, Apple Watch, Beats products, and HomePod. Further, it provides AppleCare support and cloud services store services; and operates various platforms, including the App Store that allow customers to discover and download applications and digital content, such as books, music, video, games, and podcasts. Additionally, the company offers various services, such as Apple Arcade, a game subscription service; Apple Fitness+, a personalized fitness service; Apple Music, which offers users a curated listening experience with on-demand radio stations; Apple News+, a subscription news and magazine service; Apple TV+, which offers exclusive original content; Apple Card, a co-branded credit card; and Apple Pay, a cashless payment service, as well as licenses its intellectual property. The company serves consumers, and small and mid-sized businesses; and the education, enterprise, and government markets. It distributes third-party applications for its products through the App Store. The company also sells its products through its retail and online stores, and direct sales force; and third-party cellular network carriers, wholesalers, retailers, and resellers. Apple Inc. was incorporated in 1977 and is headquartered in Cupertino, California.’</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The total number of unique words in the dataset was 63734 (number of characters: 5910439), on average each company description was 147 words long, with 96% of documents having between 45 and 272 words.</p>

<p>Documents were preprocessed to reduce noise and vocabulary size (and in consequence, compute requirements).
The following steps were applied:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Removal numbers</li>
  <li>Removal punctuation/symbols</li>
  <li>Removal diacritics</li>
  <li>Lower case</li>
  <li>Removal multiple whitespaces</li>
  <li>Removal words shorter than 3 characters</li>
  <li>Removal words occurring in less than 5 documents</li>
</ul>

<p>After this preprocessing, the unique words were 6897 (4165286, or ~70% of the raw version), document length was 86 (most within 25-177).</p>

<p><em>Sparse embeddings</em>. Preprocessed description were embedded using a TF-IDF Transformers as in <a href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.feature_extraction.text.TfidfVectorizer.html">sklearn.feature_extraction.text.TfidfVectorizer</a> using a vocabulary size of 1000.</p>

<p><em>Word embedding vectors</em>. <a href="https://radimrehurek.com/gensim/models/word2vec.html">Gensim</a> Word2Vec implementation was applied to preprocessed company descriptions.
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.04212">Word2Vec applied to Recommendation: Hyperparameters Matter</a></p>

<p><em>Sentece contextual embeddings</em>
We used <a href="https://huggingface.co/BAAI/bge-small-en-v1.5">bge_small_1.5</a> a state of the art contextual embeddings showing best performances on several tasks on the <a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/mteb/leaderboard">MTEB leaderboard</a> at its embedding dimensionality size (384) at the time of this post. Raw text data was encoded (i.e. no preprocessing) taking advantage of sub-word Tokenizer.
<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2309.07597.pdf">C-Pack: Packaged Resources To Advance General Chinese Embedding</a></p>

<p>When we visualize these t-SNE embeddings and color-code each point (representing a company) based on its sector, a fascinating pattern emerges.</p>

<p>To enrich our visualization further, we’ve integrated market capitalization data by varying the size of each point based on the company’s market cap. This addition provides a layer of financial insight, allowing viewers to instantly gauge the economic scale of each company within its cluster. Larger points signify companies with greater market caps, offering a quick visual reference to distinguish between major players and smaller entities within the same sector. This enhanced visualization technique transforms our dataset into an intuitive, informative map of the stock market, where both industry relationships and financial stature are simultaneously conveyed, providing stakeholders with a comprehensive understanding of market dynamics at a glance.</p>

<p>Example visualizations obtained by this technique:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/TF.gif" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/WV.gif" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/BGE.gif" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p>We can observe distinct clusters forming, such as a cluster of utilities or bitcoin miners, indicating that our embeddings effectively capture semantic and business similarities. This visualization not only confirms the robustness of our embedding techniques but also showcases the potential of t-SNE to reveal underlying industry dynamics and relationships that might not be apparent from traditional analysis methods.</p>

<h1 id="insights">Insights</h1>

<p>Leveraging the sophisticated visualization model we’ve developed, we transition from merely presenting data to extracting actionable insights. One intriguing application of our model is the identification of misclassified companies using a k-nearest neighbors (k-NN) classifier. This approach isn’t about pointing out errors in a simplistic manner; rather, it’s about uncovering the nuanced, sometimes overlooked aspects of a company’s operations that might not be fully captured by traditional sector classifications.</p>

<p>The k-NN classifier works by examining the ‘neighbors’—in this case, other companies—closest to a given company in our multidimensional embedding space. If a company is found to be consistently closer to neighbors from a different sector than its own, it raises an interesting question: might this company be operating in a way that straddles the line between two sectors? This could indicate a firm that, while officially classified in one sector, is leveraging technologies, methodologies, or market approaches typically associated with another.</p>

<p>Such an approach can unearth fascinating cases of companies operating at the intersection of sectors, potentially harnessing competitive advantages from this unique positioning. These firms might be innovating in ways that traditional sector classifications and analyses fail to capture fully, making them particularly intriguing for investors, analysts, and industry watchers.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/VEE.png" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p>Take, for example, <a href="https://www.veeva.com/">Veeva Systems</a>. Officially classified within the healthcare sector, our analysis might reveal it to be closely associated with technology companies in the embedding space. This isn’t a misclassification in the traditional sense but a reflection of Veeva’s business model that leverages cloud-based software solutions specifically for the life sciences industry. By operating at the nexus of healthcare and technology, Veeva exemplifies how companies can transcend traditional industry boundaries to carve out unique, competitive niches. Through our model, we can identify and highlight such companies, offering deeper insights into their operations and potentially redefining how we think about industry sectors and innovation.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/INTU.png" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p>Similarly, <a href="https://www.intuit.com/">Intuit</a>. Commonly recognized within the technology sector, our refined analysis could highlight its profound association with financial services in the embedding space. This observation isn’t about mislabeling in a conventional sense but rather underscores Intuit’s innovative approach to blending technology with financial services. Known for products like TurboTax, QuickBooks, and Mint, Intuit integrates advanced technology to simplify complex financial tasks for individuals and small businesses. Standing at the crossroads of technology and financial services, Intuit serves as a prime example of how modern companies can blur the lines between traditional sectors to forge distinct, competitive advantages. By leveraging our analytical model, we can spotlight such organizations, providing a deeper understanding of their business strategies and challenging our preconceived notions of industry classifications. This approach not only illuminates the multifaceted operations of companies like Intuit but also encourages a broader perspective on the evolving landscape of industry sectors and innovation.</p>

<h1 id="further-developments">Further developments</h1>

<p>Our exploration into the nuanced dynamics of the stock market takes another leap forward when we incorporate market performance data into our visualization. By color-coding each company based on its market performance over a specified period, we introduce an additional layer of analysis that can reveal broader market trends and sector-specific movements. This visual differentiation allows stakeholders to quickly identify which sectors are outperforming others and spot potential trends as they develop in real-time. For instance, a cluster of technology companies might show a predominant color indicating strong recent growth, suggesting a trend that could merit closer attention from investors and analysts alike.</p>

<p>The potential for further expansion and refinement of our model is substantial, particularly through the integration of comprehensive and detailed regulatory filings such as 10-K reports filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC). These annual reports, required from publicly traded companies, offer a complete and in-depth overview of a company’s financial condition, including its balance sheet, income statement, cash flow, and a detailed discussion of its business operations. By analyzing these documents, we can gain deeper insights into the financial health and strategic directions of companies across various sectors. This data could significantly enhance our model by adding a new layer to our analysis, allowing us to better understand a company’s performance, risk factors, and growth prospects.</p>

<p>Incorporating 10-K filings, along with other balance sheet regulatory filings, could also allow us to refine our company embeddings further. By examining the financial statements and management discussion and analysis (MD&amp;A) sections of these reports, we can identify nuanced semantic relationships between companies based on financial health, investment in research and development, and market strategies. For instance, if companies A and B both report similar strategies in their 10-K filings regarding market expansion or technology investment, it might suggest a perceived or real similarity between these companies, beyond what is captured through traditional business descriptions or sector classifications. This approach can reveal underlying patterns and connections within the financial markets, enhancing our model’s ability to predict market dynamics and company performance.</p>

<p>Another compelling application of our enhanced visualization and analysis model is the identification of companies whose market returns significantly diverge from those of their closest neighbors in the embedding space. This exploration can yield valuable insights, highlighting firms that are outliers within their presumed peer group. Such discrepancies between a company’s performance and that of its neighbors may signal unique strengths or challenges that set it apart.</p>

<p>For instance, within a cluster of companies that are closely related in terms of business operations and market sector, most might show similar financial performance trends due to shared market conditions and industry-specific factors. However, if one company within this group exhibits markedly better or worse returns, it prompts a deeper investigation. These outliers could be benefiting from innovative business models, superior management, or emerging technologies that confer a competitive edge. Conversely, they might be facing unique challenges, regulatory issues, or operational inefficiencies that their peers have successfully navigated.</p>

<p>Identifying such companies is not merely an academic exercise; it offers practical, actionable insights for investors, analysts, and corporate strategists. For investors, these outliers may represent potential opportunities for above-average returns, assuming the divergence is due to positive factors that the market has not yet fully recognized. For corporate strategists and business analysts, understanding why these companies stand apart may provide critical lessons in competitive advantage, risk management, and strategic planning.</p>

<p>This approach underscores the power of data science in uncovering hidden patterns and opportunities within complex datasets. By moving beyond traditional sector analysis and leveraging advanced embeddings and machine learning techniques, we can uncover nuanced insights that are not readily apparent through conventional analysis. These insights can guide more informed decision-making, helping stakeholders to identify not just the companies that are currently leading the market, but also those poised for future success or in need of strategic redirection.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="NLP" /><category term="finance" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Background]]></summary></entry></feed>